Guide to the American Civil Liberties Union of North Carolina Records, 1960-2020; 1960-ongoing and undated RL.00012
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Executive Director Office Series, 1965-2001 and undated, 90 boxes
  - 1960s-1970s Files Subseries
    - 1969-1970 Files
      - Administrative Executive Office Files, 1960s-1970s:
        - Executive indeterminate mail (unsubstantive) (Box 10)
        - File Department (Box 10)
    - 1970-1971 Files
      Primarily the correspondence, administrative, and subject files of Betsy Brinson as Executive Secretary (i.e., Director). Includes Board of Directors files as well as reports, newsletters, publicity, and conference files. Arranged internally in original alphabetical order.
      - ACLU Files (National):
        - Academic Freedom Committee (Box 10)
        - Biennial Report and Conference (Box 10)
        - Board of Directors--minutes (Box 11)
        - Board of Directors--miscellaneous (Box 11)
        - Church State Committee (Box 11)
        - Communications Media Committee (Box 11)
        - Current membership income (Box 11)
        - Due Process Committee (Box 11)
        - Equality Committee (Box 11)
        - Free Speech/Association Committee (Box 11)
        - Labor-Business Committee (Box 11)
        - Memos to NCCLU-reports and statements (Box 11)
        - Position papers-prepared for Biennial Conference (Box 11)
        - Press releases (Box 11)
        - Publicity (Box 11)
      - Addresses (Box 11)
      - Annual meeting (Box 11)
      - Board appointments and related correspondence (Box 12)
      - Board correspondence (Box 12)
      - Board meetings, agendas (Box 12)
      - Chapter correspondence (Box 12)
      - Chapter development and by-laws (Box 12)
      - Chapter newsletters (Box 12)
      - Committee newsletters (Box 12)
      - Common Cause (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, ACLU, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, membership, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, miscellaneous, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Correspondence, other affiliates (minutes, etc.) (Box 12)
      - Draft repeal (Box 12)
      - Fundraising and membership (Box 12)
      - Inside ACLU, 1970 (Box 12)
      - Leadership Conferences on Civil Rights (Box 12)
      - Legislative action (Box 12)
      - Legislative newsletters (Box 12)
      - Letter samples for mailing (Box 12)
      - Letters to new members (Box 12)
      - Membership questionnaires (Box 12)
      - Membership solicitation (Box 13)
      - Miscellaneous materials (Box 13)
      - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation (Box 13)
      - Newsletters, other affiliates, 2 folders (Box 13)
      - Nominations for Board of Directors, 1971 (Box 13)
      - North Carolinians Against the Death Penalty (Box 13)
      - Organized Crime Control Act, S. 30 (Box 13)
      - Press releases, 1970 (Box 13)
      - Press releases, other affiliates, 1970 (Box 13)
      - Promotional materials and literature (Box 13)
      - Related articles and pamphlets, 1970 (Box 13)
      - Senate Subcommittee on Constitutional Rights (Box 13)
      - Women's rights (Box 13)
    - 1972 Files
      Primarily the files of Betsy Brinson as Executive Secretary. Includes Board of Directors correspondence and press releases, as well as numerous subject files. Arranged in original alphabetical order.
      - ACLU Files (National):
        - Academic Freedom Committee Minutes (Box 13)
        - Activity Reports (Box 14)
        - Board of Directors, minutes (Box 14)
        - Church-State Committee, minutes (Box 14)
        - Communication Media Committee, minutes (Box 14)
        - Conferences (Box 14)
        - Correspondence (Box 14)
        - Due Process Committee, minutes (Box 14)
        - Equality Committee, minutes (Box 14)
        - Free Speech/Association Committee, minutes (Box 14)
        - Juvenile Rights Project (Box 14)
        - Press releases (Box 14)
        - Steering Committee (Box 14)
      - Bank Record Project (Box 14)
      - Board correspondence (Box 14)
      - Draft repeal (Box 14)
      - General correspondence (Box 14)
      - Leadership Conference on Civil Rights bulletins (Box 14)
      - Legislative correspondence, national (Box 14)
      - Legislative program (Box 14)
      - Marijuana Repeal (Box 14)
      - Membership solicitation (Box 14)
      - National Committee Against Repressive Legislation (Box 14)
      - Press releases (Box 14)
      - Project ideals (Box 14)
      - Promotional materials (Box 14)
      - Public Affairs Forum (Box 14)
      - Speakers Bureau (Box 14)
      - Speeches, articles, special reports, 2 folders (Box 15)
      - Virginia affiliate (Box 15)
      - Women's rights, 2 folders (Box 15)
    - 1972-1973 Files
      Primarily the files of Betsy Brinson as Executive Secretary. Arranged in alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - Affiliate information (Box 15)
      - Amnesty (Box 15)
      - Annual Meeting, 1972 (Box 15)
      - Annual Meeting, 1973 (Box 15)
      - Annual Meeting and nominations, 1973 (Box 15)
      - Chapter correspondence and materials (Box 15)
      - Civil Liberties Seminar (Box 15)
      - Impeach Nixon Campaign, 2 folders (Box 16)
      - Legislative Committee planning and correspondence (Box 16)
      - Legislature correspondence (Box 16)
      - Membership income (Box 16)
      - Membership solicitations (Box 16)
      - Miscellaneous solicitations (Box 16)
      - Neier, Aryeh (Box 16)
      - Newspaper clippings (Box 16)
      - NC Political Prisoners Committee (Box 16)
      - Nuclear reactor materials (Box 16)
      - Projects (Box 16)
      - Rights if arrested (Box 16)
      - Speakers Bureau (Box 16)
      - Student rights (Box 16)
      - Women's rights correspondence (Box 16)
      - Wright, Marion, correspondence (Box 16)
    - 1974 Files
      Primarily the files of Betsy Brinson, Executive Secretary (e.g. Director) and George Gardner as Executive Director; arranged in original alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU correspondence (National Office) (Box 16)
      - Affiliate states (Box 16)
      - Appalachian file, office (Box 16)
      - Behavior Modification, Butner Facility, folder 1 of 2 (Box 16)
      - Behavior Modification, Butner Facility, folder 2 of 2 (Box 17)
      - Biennial Conference (Box 17)
      - Board correspondence (Box 17)
      - Budget and Finance Committee (Box 17)
      - Chapter board members, chapter offices (Box 17)
      - Chapter correspondence (Box 17)
      - Criminal victim compensation (Box 17)
      - Every-Member-Get-A-Member Campaign (Box 17)
      - Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 (Box 17)
      - Fox, Herman, correspondence (Box 17)
      - General correspondence (Box 17)
      - Insurance (Box 17)
      - Invoices (Box 17)
      - Know Your Rights cards (Box 17)
      - Manpower Program (Box 17)
      - Marijuana repeal (Box 17)
      - NC Political Prisoners Committee (Box 17)
      - Parks, Mrs. Helen (letters of George Cleland) (Box 17)
      - Personnel Committee (Box 17)
      - Press releases (Box 17)
      - Student rights, 2 folders (Box 17)
      - Summer Internship Program (Box 17)
      - Textbook evaluation (Box 18)
    - 1975-1976 Files
      Primarily the files of George Gardner as executive director; arranged in original alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU correspondence (Box 18)
      - ACLU list of issues before Subject Matter Committee (Box 18)
      - ACLU National Board Executive Committee (Box 18)
      - ACLU Washington Legislative Office (Box 18)
      - Administrative assistant (Box 18)
      - Affiliate correspondence (Box 18)
      - Benefit concert, Paul Sebo (Box 18)
      - Board agenda and minutes (Box 18)
      - Board correspondence, NCCLU (Box 18)
      - Board resolutions, committee reports (Box 18)
      - Book orders, posters, etc. (Box 18)
      - Chapter correspondence (Box 18)
      - Chapter development (Box 18)
      - Civil Liberties, ACLU newsletter (Box 18)
      - Civil Liberties Review, subscription campaign (Box 18)
      - Committee appointments (Box 18)
      - Committee correspondence (Box 18)
      - Committee on Laws, focused education, NC (Box 18)
      - Court watching (Box 18)
      - Dockets NCCLU and ACLU (Box 19)
      - Employee benefits, National Office Program (Box 19)
      - Expense account (Box 19)
      - Field Foundation Grant (Box 19)
      - Financial (Box 19)
      - Finlator, W. W. (Box 19)
      - Form letter, samples (Box 19)
      - Foundation associates (Box 19)
      - Fundraising (Box 19)
      - Fundraising, auction (Box 19)
      - General correspondence, 2 folders (Box 19)
      - General counsel (Box 19)
      - Gora, Joel (Box 19)
      - Know Your Rights cards (Box 19)
      - Legal aid (Box 19)
      - Legal director, ACLU litigation (Box 19)
      - Legislative brochure, 1975 (Box 19)
      - Legislative Committee, national legislation (Box 19)
      - Legislative Program, 1976, NCCLU (Box 19)
      - Liberty (Box 19)
      - Liberty Fund Drive (Box 19)
      - Long Range Planning Committee (Box 20)
      - Membership Development (Box 20)
      - Morgan (Box 20)
      - Mulholland Committee (Box 20)
      - National Development Council (Box 20)
      - National Military Discharge Upgrade Project (Box 20)
      - Newsletters, affiliates (Box 20)
      - Newsletters, affiliates (Box 20)
      - Newsletters, NCCLU Chapters (Box 20)
      - Newspaper clippings, folder 1 of 2 (Box 20)
      - Newspaper clippings, folder 2 of 2 (Box 21)
      - Nominating Committee, vita, 1976 (Box 21)
      - North Carolina black lawyers (Box 21)
      - North Carolina Legal Defense Fund (Box 21)
      - North Carolina Statutes (Box 21)
      - Nut letters (Box 21)
      - Office log (Box 21)
      - Personnel Committee, NCCLU (Box 21)
      - President, NCCLU (Box 21)
      - Press releases, NCCLU, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Price, Julian (Box 21)
      - Primary membership responsibility (Box 21)
      - Printing type set (Box 21)
      - Prisoner's form letter (Box 21)
      - Programs (Box 21)
      - Renewal Campaign (Box 21)
      - Requests for assistance, 1975 (Box 21)
      - Requests for assistance, 1976, 2 folders (Box 21)
      - Resumes, Director, NCCLU (Box 21)
      - Sevareid, Eric (Box 22)
      - Silver, Frank K. (Box 22)
      - Southern Affiliate Conference (Box 22)
      - Southern Regional Office, ACLU (Box 22)
      - Stone, I.F., film (Box 22)
      - Subject Matter Committee (Box 22)
      - Suspended, purged renewal effort (Box 22)
      - Unitarian-Universalist mail lists (Box 22)
      - Volunteers (Box 22)
    - 1977 Files
      Primarily the files of George Gardner as executive director. In original alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU Board and Executive Committee minutes, 1977 (Box 22)
      - ACLU correspondence (Box 22)
      - ACLU National Board/Executive Committee (Box 22)
      - ACLU staff liaison (Jay Miller) (Box 22)
      - ACLU Washington Legislative Office (Box 22)
      - Affiliates, correspondence (Box 22)
      - Biennial Conferences (Box 22)
      - Board correspondence, NCCLU (Box 22)
      - Book orders, etc. (Box 22)
      - CAF grant proposals (Box 22)
      - Chapters (Box 22)
      - Dockets/NCCLU?, ACLU (Box 23)
      - Executive Director's Conference, 1977 (Box 23)
      - Frank Porter Graham Award (Box 23)
      - General correspondence, 2 folders (Box 23)
      - General counsel, NCCLU (Box 23)
      - Inmate Grievance Committee (Box 23)
      - Know Your Rights cards (Box 23)
      - Labor relations (Box 23)
      - Legal Director, ACLU, litigation (Box 23)
      - Legislative Committee, NCCLU (Box 23)
      - Membership development (Box 23)
      - National Development Council/Steering Committee, NDC (Box 23)
      - Newspaper clippings, 1976-1977 (Box 23)
      - Projects (Box 23)
      - Requests for assistance, folders 1-3 of 5 (Box 23)
      - Requests for assistance, folders 4-5 of 5 (Box 24)
      - Southern Regional Office, ACLU (Box 24)
      - Steering Committee (Box 24)
      - Steering/Development Committee, NDC (Box 24)
    - 1978-1979 Files
      Primarily the files of George Gardner as executive director. In alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU National Board/Executive Committee, 3 folders (Box 24)
      - ACLU correspondence (Box 24)
      - ACLU executive director correspondence (Box 24)
      - ACLU Biennial, 1979 (Box 24)
      - ACLU Washington Legislative Office (Box 24)
      - Affiliates correspondence (Box 24)
      - Board agendas and meetings (Box 25)
      - Board correspondence, NCCLU (Box 25)
      - Burford, Walter W. (Box 25)
      - Chapters (Box 25)
      - Committee appointments, NCCLU (Box 25)
      - Farmworkers Legal Service of NC (Box 25)
      - Foundations (Box 25)
      - General correspondence, incl. telegram from ACLU-NC to Jesse Helms, 2 folders (Box 25)
      - Handicapped (Box 25)
      - Inmate Grievance Committee (F. Morrison) (Box 25)
      - Inmate medical care (Box 25)
      - Legal committee, NCCLU litigation (Box 25)
      - Liberty, NCCLU newsletter (Box 25)
      - Literature lists (Box 25)
      - Litigation (Box 25)
      - Membership Committee (Box 25)
      - Membership development (Box 25)
      - Morgan, Senator Robert (Box 25)
      - Newspaper clippings, 2 folders (Box 26)
      - Requests for assistance, 4 folders (Box 26)
      - Spring retreat, 1978 (Box 26)
      - Spring retreat, 1979 (Box 26)
      - Summer intern (Box 26)
  - 1980s Files Subseries, 1980-1990
    Includes many files assembled by the first Executive Director, Norman B. Smith, but the bulk of the files are from the 1980s and were assembled during George Gardner's term. The majority of the materials take the form of correspondence, chiefly relating to ACLU (national and regional), attorney activities, committee work, and case files either for litigation or investigation. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
    - 1980 Executive Office Files
      Primarily the files of George Gardner. Arranged in original alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU Correspondence (Box 26)
      - ACLU Executive Director's correspondence (Box 27)
      - ACLU National Board, Executive Committee (Box 27)
      - Administrative Assistant (Box 27)
      - Affiliate correspondence (Box 27)
      - Annual reports (Box 27)
      - Board correspondence (Box 27)
      - Children's Rights Committee (Box 27)
      - Fundraising (Box 27)
      - General correspondence (Box 27)
      - General correspondence, 2 folders (Box 27)
      - Humanities (Box 27)
      - Legislation, National (Box 27)
      - Membership Committee: minutes and monthly reports (Box 27)
      - Membership development (Box 27)
      - Ms. subscriptions (Box 27)
      - Nominating Committee (Box 27)
      - Quaker House (Box 27)
      - Requests for assistance, folders 1-2 of 3 (Box 27)
      - Requests for assistance, folder 3 of 3 (Box 28)
      - Spring retreat, 1980 (Box 28)
    - 1981-1982 Executive Office Files
      Chiefly the files of George Gardner. Arranged in original alphabetical sequence. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - ACLU correspondence and memoranda (Box 28)
      - Affiliate chapter relations (Box 28)
      - Affiliate correspondence (Box 28)
      - Annual reports: chapter committee (Box 28)
      - Board agendas, meetings, and minutes (Box 28)
      - Board correspondence (Box 28)
      - Chapters: correspondence (Box 28)
      - Chapters: development (Box 28)
      - Committee appointments (Box 28)
      - Committee correspondence (Box 28)
      - Dialogues on Justice in Greensboro (Box 28)
      - Dispute resolution (Box 28)
      - Finance Committee (Box 28)
      - General correspondence, 1981 (Box 28)
      - General correspondence, 1982 (Box 29)
      - Glasser, Ira (1981 Apr. visit) (Box 29)
      - Legal Committee (Box 29)
      - Legislation, national, 2 folders (Box 29)
      - Mason, John (Box 29)
      - Membership Development Conference, Washington, 1982 (Box 29)
      - Membership questionnaires (Box 29)
      - O'Neill, Frank (Box 29)
      - Press Conference (Box 29)
      - Primary membership responsibility (Box 29)
      - Publicity handbook (Box 29)
      - Requests for assistance (Box 29)
      - Requests for assistance (Box 29)
      - Spring concert (Box 30)
      - Spring retreat, 1981 (Box 30)
      - Spring retreat, 1982 (Box 30)
      - Washington legislative office (Box 30)
    - 1983 Executive Office Files
      From the files of George Gardner. Arranged in alphabetical order. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - Affiliate correspondence (Box 30)
      - Board agenda and memoranda (Box 30)
      - Board correspondence (Box 30)
      - Chapters, correspondence (Box 30)
      - Finance correspondence (Box 30)
      - General correspondence (Box 30)
      - Membership development: direct mail campaign (Box 30)
      - Requests for assistance (Box 30)
      - Requests for assistance (Box 30)
    - 1983-1986 Executive Office Files, 1971-1986
      Almost all are correspondence and administrative files kept by Gardner, with a few assembled by Norman Smith during his earlier tenure as Executive Director and dating from the 1970s. Researchers should be aware that privacy laws govern the use or publication of information in these files.
      - Administrative Files, 1966-1988:
        - Abortion and Woman's Choice Materials, 1977-1982 (Box 31)
        - ACLU 1984 (Box 31)
        - Babcock Foundation (Box 31)
        - Biennial Conference, 1985 (Box 31)
        - NCCLU Board of Directors Materials, 1984-1986 (Box 31)
        - Brooks, 1982-1986 (Box 31)
        - Budget Report, 1982 (Box 31)
        - Campbell University Law School (Box 31)
        - Chapel Hill, 1977-1984 (Box 31)
        - Chapters, Development, 1976-1986 (Box 31)
        - Asheville-Henderson Chapter, 1978-1986 (Box 31)
        - Chapel Hill, Dupl. (Box 31)
        - Charlotte, 1977-1984, 2 folders (Box 32)
        - Raleigh, 1969-1984 (Box 32)
        - Greensboro, 1977-1984 (Box 32)
        - Cherokee Indians of Hoke (Box 32)
        - Cumulative Membership Income (CMI) (Box 32)
        - Committee rosters (Box 32)
        - Court watching (Box 32)
        - Cumulative Membership Income (Box 32)
        - DeSoto, Phyllis (Box 32)
        - Fairs, NCCLU Fund Raisers (Box 32)
        - 1977 Fall Fundraiser (Box 32)
        - Greensboro Justice Fund, CWP Suit, ACLU (Box 32)
        - Greensboro National Bank (Box 33)
        - North Carolina Humanities Committee (Box 33)
        - NC Civil Liberties (Box 33)
        - NCCLU, 1986-1987 Board (Box 33)
        - NCCLU, Cooperating Attorneys (Box 33)
        - Civil Liberties, miscellaneous (Box 33)
        - Civil Liberties, accounting (Box 33)
        - Miscellaneous papers and minutes (Box 33)
        - Budgets, notes and clippings (Box 33)
        - NCCLU Finance Committee (Box 33)
        - NCCLU, 6 month committee (Box 33)
        - Dan Pollitt Roast, 1983 (Box 33)
        - NCCLU correspondence, 1982 (Box 33)
        - Annual reports, 1982 (Box 34)
        - Miscellaneous activities (Box 34)
        - 1982, Rejections for assistance or legal aid (Box 34)
        - Copying requests and charges (Box 34)
        - 1983, Rejections for assistance or legal service (Box 34)
        - 1983, Requests for assistance (Box 34)
        - Closed (Box 34)
        - Miscellaneous cases, 1983 (Box 34)
        - Memoranda, 1986 (Box 35)
        - Articles on Second Amendment (Box 35)
        - Legal committee, 1978-1984 (Box 35)
        - Legal committee, 1981-1986 (Box 35)
        - Katha Pollitt articles (Box 35)
        - Legal committee chair (Box 35)
        - Legal committee, materials (Box 35)
        - Legal department, ACLU lawyer (Box 35)
        - Legal director and counsel, ACLU (Box 35)
        - Litigation, Coble/Webster v. Proffitt [empty folder] (Box 35)
        - Litigation, Zoro Guice (Box 35)
        - Cooperating attorneys, guidelines, fees, etc. (Box 35)
        - Notes (Box 35)
        - Legal files (Box 35)
        - CLU docket materials (Box 35)
        - Miscellaneous legal files (Box 35)
        - Miscellaneous files (Box 36)
        - Miscellaneous files, 1978 (Box 36)
          Includes correspondence between the NCCLU and politicians, citizens asking for assistance, and members. Also includes receipts from misc. transactions and some legal documents
        - Miscellaneous files, 1977 (Box 36)
          Includes some legal documents, receipts, and correspondence.
        - Miscellaneous legal files (Box 36)
        - Correspondence and documents concerning misc. prisoners (Box 36)
        - Legal documents and correspondence about cases and/or requests for assistance., 3 folders (Box 36)
        - Norman Smith, rejection letters and case files (Box 37)
        - Norman Smith, correspondence (Box 37)
        - Norman Smith, misc. files (Box 37)
          Includes correspondence, legislation, newsletters, and other documents.
        - Civil liberties, etc. (Box 37)
        - From unmarked file, 5 folders (Box 37)
          Includes briefs, newspaper clippings and correspondence. Mostly from Norman Smith.
        - From unmarked file, 3 folders (Box 37)
          Includes documents about issues, litigation, correspondence, receipts, etc. Mostly from Norman Smith.
        - Miscellaneous files (Box 38)
          Includes documents on the issues of marijuana use and name change, resignation letter of Betsy Brinson, and newspaper clippings
        - Board of directors, chapter presidents (Box 38)
        - Miscellaneous files (Box 38)
          Includes the Journal for Scholastic Media, Volume XXVI No. 5, and the Liberty newsletter, Vol. 17 No. 2.
        - NCCLU Foundation (Box 38)
        - Hazel and Spaulding - witnesses, extra exhibits (from unmarked folder), 4 folders
          Includes correspondence, notes, and legal documents about several cases.
        - Financial files (Box 38)
        - Miscellaneous legal files (Box 38)
        - Biennial conferences (Box 38)
        - Notes and memos (Box 39)
        - Board of Directors, minutes and budgets, 1969-1981 (Box 39)
        - Board of Directors, minutes and budgets, 1970-1980 (Box 39)
        - Agendas and Minutes, 1984-1987 (Box 39)
          Includes minutes and agendas from the Board of Directors meetings, Finance Committee meetings, and Legal Committee meetings.
      - Correspondence Files, 1973-1986:
        - ACLU National Office Correspondence, 1983-1986, 4 folders (Box 40)
        - Board President correspondence, 1975-1984, 2 folders (Box 40)
        - Committee correspondence, 1981-1986 (Box 40)
        - General correspondence, 1977-1986, 2 folders (Box 40)
        - General correspondence, 1980-1986, 2 folders (Box 41)
        - NCCLU correspondence, 1985-1986 (Box 41)
        - NCCLU Executive Committee, Board of Directors, 1981-1982 (Box 41)
        - Correspondence, 1981-1982, 2 folders (Box 41)
        - Correspondence, 1982 (Box 41)
        - CLU - 1982 requests for assistance (Box 41)
        - Letters from attorneys, 1982 (Box 41)